"The Highest Antioxidant:
Apple, Bean, Berry, Lentil, or Nut?"
An apple a day has been
associated with as much as
a 35 percent lower risk
of premature death,
but which apple is best?
Whichever apple
you'll eat the most.
So, eat your favorite apple.
But if you don't care
which apple you eat,
or you're just curious,
which apple has the highest
antioxidant content:
Fuji, Gala, Golden Delicious,
Granny Smith, Pink Lady,
or Red Delicious?
Anytime you want to check the
antioxidant content of foods,
nothing beats this free database
of more than 3,000 foods.
For apples,
Granny gets the gold,
with more than
twice as many antioxidants
than Golden Delicious apples.
Interestingly, antioxidant
content roughly corresponds
with the ability
to lower cholesterol levels
within one month
for those randomized to eat
an apple a day.
Annurca apples beat
Granny Smith, but presumably,
it's because study participants
got two Annurcas a day
versus just one of the others,
because they were
about half the size.
But two apples
even when they're half the size,
have more overall surface area,
and the magic
may be in the peel.
If you randomize people to eat
apples with or without the peel,
you see a significant boost
in artery function
within an hour
of peel consumption.
So, don't peel your apples.
For other foods, the antioxidant
spread can be even greater.
Check out nuts.
Two nuts pull way ahead,
with the top nut having nearly
75 times the antioxidants
than the bottom nut.
Which do you think is which?
Want to pause and guess?
Walnuts for the win!
Followed by pecans,
then pistachios,
and who would have guessed
almonds would be
way down here at the bottom?
Walnuts also have
the highest omega-3 content,
by a large margin,
beat out other nuts
in suppressing the growth
of cancer cells
in a Petri dish.
And walnuts are
the only nuts shown
to markedly improve
human artery function.
Blackberries
beat out blueberries
for antioxidant capacity.
The beans surprised me.
What do you think fits the bill
for best bean,
at least
from an antioxidant perspective?
Want to pause and take bets?
The lowest on the leaderboard:
chickpeas.
Holy hummus!
The mightiest free radical
fighter is the fava bean,
with kidneys and pintos
neck and neck for number two.
Lentils were
another big surprise.
I would have guessed
black or red lentils
to be up there with brown
or green at the bottom.
But check this out.
Green lentils have
about four times
the antioxidant power
of red ones!